Martha Lipton papers, 1938-2006 C30
Indiana University Archives
Martha Lipton papers
1939-2006
1939-1977
Indiana University Archives
Lipton, Martha
C30
1.4 cubic feet 2 boxes
Martha Lipton was a prolific performer at the New York Metropolitan Opera as a mezzo-soprano for sixteen seasons. She was a soloist who sang under the direction of many renowned conductors before coming to Indiana University Bloomington as a Professor of Voice in 1960. This collection contains professional promotional materials, clippings and performance programs spanning her career.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Biographical Note
Born in New York City on April 6, 1913, Martha Lipton went on to win a scholarship to the Julliard School, graduating in 1942 and the following year becoming an Honorary Member of Delta Omicron, a worldwide music fraternity at the Cincinnati Conservatory of Music. In 1944 she made her debut with the New York Opera Company and went on to also perform with the New York Metropolitan Opera. Her 401st and last performance with the Met was in 1961. During her career Lipton performed three dozen roles in four languages. She also sang under famous conductors such as Bruno Walter, Leonard Bernstein, and Leopold Stowkowski.
Lipton came to Indiana University as a professor of voice in 1960 where she also performed in many IU opera productions. The most notable being Puccini's "Aida" in which she played the role of Amneris in IU's outdoor stage production at Memorial Stadium in July and August of 1963. While she officially retired from teaching in 1983 with the rank of professor emeritus, she continued to teach part-time until her death on November 28, 2006.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into three series: Biographical, Correspondence, and Professional files.
Scope and Content Note
Spanning the years 1939-1987, the Martha Lipton papers are organized into three series: Biographical, Correspondence, and Professional files.
The Biographical series includes clippings of reviews of her performances and biographical interviews (undated, 1939-2004). There are a few clippings from the Bloomington Herald Times. The Indiana University Emeritus Club Honors file (1983) contains the certificate award naming her as a member.
The Correspondence series (1966-2006) includes primarily personal correspondence with her father and mother, and from current and former students in support of her nomination for distinguished professorship.
The Professional files series includes performance programs (1939-1987) of performances she played in various venues and countries. The Promotional Materials file (undated) contains posters promoting her talent and roles performed with reviewers' quotes from newspapers and magazines. The Stage Sets and Performance Notes (undated) is a small notebook with sketches of stage props performer's locations and movement directions on the sets of three productions; Samson, Tristan and Isolde, and The ballad of Baby Doe. Notes are written in French, German, and English.
Separated Material
A hand fan used in a performance was pulled from the collection and is housed in the Archives memorabilia cabinet.
191 photographs of family, performances, and promotional head shots were pulled from the collection and transferred to the Archives Photograph Collection.
Related Material
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database: http://webapp1.dlib.indiana.edu/archivesphotos/
Acquisition Information
Accession 2012/152
Provenance
Transferred from the IU Music Library in 2012.
Appraisal
Multiple copies of promotional materials were pulled from the collection and recycled.
Mezzo-sopranos --Archives; Opera --Study and teaching (higher) --Indiana --Bloomington --History --Sources.; Lipton, Martha -- Archives
- Biographical, 1939-2004
  - Clippings (Box 1)
    - 1939-1987 (Box 1)
    - 1947-2004 (Box 1)
  - Indiana University Emeritus Club Honors, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 1)
    - 1938-1939 (Box 2)
    - 1944-1952 (Box 2)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1966-2006; undated
  - Personal, 1966-2006 (Box 1)
  - Students, 1975-1977; undated (Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    (RESTRICTED)
- Professional Files, 1939-1987; undated
  - Performance Programs (Box 1)
    - 1939 (Box 1)
    - 1941 (Box 1)
    - 1944 (Box 1)
    - 1945 (Box 1)
    - 1946 (Box 1)
    - 1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948 (Box 1)
    - 1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951 (Box 1)
    - 1952 (Box 1)
    - 1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1)
    - 1955 (Box 1)
    - 1956 (Box 1)
    - 1957 (Box 1)
    - 1958 (Box 1)
    - 1960 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
  - Promotional materials, undated (Box 1)
  - Performance prop, hand fan from Rigoletto, undated (Box 1)
  - Stage Sets and Performance Notes, undated (Box 1)
  - RESTRICTED FILES (Box 1)